Register of the Boris Souvarine papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris Souvarine papers
1925-1971
77008
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, clippings, and printed matter, relating to the French Communist Party, the Communist International, Marxism, Soviet agricultural and economic policies, and political events in twentieth-century Russia. Includes correspondence with Ekaterina Kuskova, Sergei Prokopovich, Nikolai Valentinov, and the Marx-Engels Institute (Moscow).
Souvarine, Boris
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Russian-born French journalist and author; French communist leader, 1919-1924.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, clippings, and printed matter, relating to the French Communist Party, the Communist International, Marxism, Soviet agricultural and economic policies, and political events in twentieth-century Russia. Includes correspondence with Ekaterina Kuskova, Sergei Prokopovich, Nikolai Valentinov, and the Marx-Engels Institute (Moscow).
Related Collection(s)
Additional Boris Souvarine material available at The Graduate Institute Library, Geneva, Switzerland and the Houghton Library, Harvard College Library, Harvard University
Communist International.; Kuskova, Ekaterina Dmitrievna, 1869-; Parti communiste français.; Prokopovich, Sergei.; Valentinov, N. (Nikolai), 1879-1964.; Agriculture--Soviet Union.; Communism--France.; Communism.; Socialism.; Soviet Union--Economic policy.; Soviet Union--Politics and government.
- Volsky, Nicoiai V. (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1951-1964
    - undated
  - Biographical material
  - Last will and testament, obituaries
  - Drafts, notes, articles (Box 2)
- Volsky, Valentina, correspondence, 1960-1971
- Kuskova, Ekaterina, correspondence, 1950-1957
- Prokopovich, Sergei N., correspondence, writings, etc. (Box 3)
- Marx-Engels Institute (Moscow), correspondence, 1925-1926
- Riazanov, correspondence, 1925-26
- Miscellaneous materials
- INCREMENT of March 1978: Article (handwritten in French) in Dissent (New York), 1977